Guide to the Mary Coolidge Rentschler Collection 1793-2000 (bulk, 1875-1950) MS 2999
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Manuscripts and memorabilia
  - Subseries I.C. Gordon Sohn Rentschler (1885–1948) [GSR]
    - Gordon S. Rentschler misc. magazines, 1927-1947 (Offsite-box 4, Box Mem-35)
      1927 September 17: Publications, photographs, and certificates from Gordon S. Rentschler and Mary C. Rentschler's trip to South America, september-October 1927. Includes "Number Eight" NCB magazine.
      1930: Fortune Magazine re: article on Rentschler brothers Gordon S. Rentschler and Frederick B. Rentschler, November 1930. Also 2 photographs: GSR, Orville Wright, Edward Deeds, Chas. Kettering, Sidney Waldon, John Hayard?, Edith Deeds.
      1937 June 8: Nation's Business publication, "These Tremendous Years, 1912-1937," published by the Chamber of Commerce of the U.S., Washington, D.C. Includes letter from Bird Rees, advertising manager of NB giving the book to GSR.
      1944 January 10: "Finance" magazine with photograph of Gordon S. Rentschler on the cover and article titled "How the 25 Largest Banks Rank."
      1946 January 7: "Life" magazine article featuring Gordon S. Rentschler titled "Wall Street bull market gives new life to citadel of U.S. capitalism."
      1947 December: National City Bank in-house magazine, "Number Eight" featuring a photograph of a luncheon in honor of Gordon S. Rentschler's birthday.
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, 1915 January 27 (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 1)
      Photocopy of a news clipping from "The Republican News" re: the appointment of Gordon S. Rentschler as a director of the Hooven, Owens, Rentschler Company.
    - Miscellaneous: publication, 1916 May 31 (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 2)
      Photocopy of "Princeton Alumni Weekly" re: Gordon S. Rentschler's work for the Miami Conservancy District.
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, early 1920s (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 3)
      Photocopies of news clippings re: job appointment for Gordon S. Rentschler to
      1) Miami Valley National Bank
      2) Director, then vice president of National City Bank of New York
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, 1927 February 23 (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 4)
      Photocopy of news clippings in the Hamilton Evening Journal re: Gordon S. Rentschler as presidential heir apparent to the National City Bank of New York.
    - Miscellaneous oversize news clippings re: GSR, 1927 July 24-1949 December 4 (Offsite-box Ovz-3)
      Miscellaneous oversize news clippings re: Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Farmer's and Loan Co. clippings, 1929 March-May (Offsite-box 5, Box Mem-36)
      Bound volume of original photocopies (?) of publicity clippings announcing the affiliation (merger) of the Farmer's Loan and Trust Company with the National City Bank of New York.
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, 1929 March-May (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 5-8)
      Photocopy of publicity clippings announcing the affiliation (merger) of the Farmer's Loan and Trust Company with the National City Bank of New York.
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, 1929 (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 9)
      Photocopy of press clipping re: appointment of Gordon S. Rentschler as president of National City Bank of New York.
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, circa 1935? (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 10)
      Photocopy of news clipping re: Bernard Baruch asking Gordon S. Rentschler to lease the Hippodrome, owned by National City Bank, to show the Billy Rose production, "Jumbo."
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, 1938 March 10-11 (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 11)
      Photocopies of press clippings electing Gordon S. Rentschler a life member of the Corporation of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. With Colonel Edward Deeds filling the vacated position as president of the National Cash Register Company, Dayton, Ohio.
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, 1940 July-September (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 12)
      Photocopies of news clippings re: election of Gordon S. Rentschler as National City Bank Chairman of the Board (includes original cartoons).
    - Miscellaneous: publication, 1947 November 15 (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 13)
      B. C. Forbes article on the fift foremost business leaders in the U.S.A., including Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, publication, circa 1940s (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 14)
      Publication: "The Story of the Miami Conservancy District" by the Hamilton Foundry & Machine Company. Also news clipping re: liquidation of the Miami Conservancy debt.
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, 1959 June 4 (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 15)
      News clipping featuring a copy of the 1903 Hamilton High School commencement program (commencement of Gordon S. Rentschler).
    - Miscellaneous: news clip, undated (Offsite-box Man-17, Folder 16)
      Photocopy of news clipping re: Gordon S. Rentschler's resignation from the Miami Conservancy Board, Hamilton, Ohio.
    - Death papers: correspondence, legal documents, 1947 March 22-1948 March 18 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 1)
      Correspondence, medical documents, and copy of death certificate related to Gordon S. Rentschler's health and voyage to Cuba at the time of his death.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence, 1948 February 23-May 16 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 2)
      Condolence correspondence to Mary C. Rentschler at the time of Gordon S. Rentschler's death.
    - Corning Glass Works testimonial, 1948 March 4 (Offsite-box 6, Box Mem-44)
      In memoriam illuminated pamphlet for Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence, 1948 March 4-April 22 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 3)
      Condolence correspondence to Mary C. Rentschler upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler. Correspondents are Walter Miller, J. G. Krug, Robert A. Lovett, Henry Morgenthau Jr., Cardinal Spellman, Thomas S. Lamont, Thomas Molloy, and Eugene D. Millikin.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence, 1948 March 4-May 10 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 4)
      Condolence letters to Mary C. Rentschler upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler. Correspondents include Donald Aldrich, Arthur Ballantine, Chauncey Belknap, Eleanor Ford, Robert W. Kean, John D. Rockefeller Jr., Alex Smith, and Ethel Stringfellow.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence, 1948 March 5 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 5)
      Correspondence from Caroline Hewitt, head of Miss Hewitt's Classes, to Mary C. Rentschler. Condolence letter re: death of Gordon S. Rentschler, including information that GSR was a founder of the school. Newsletter re: state of the school and its history.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence, 1948 March 5-16 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 6)
      Correspondence surrounding the death of Gordon S. Rentschler. Correspondents include Louis Naetzker, vice president National City Bank; J. P. Carter, president National City Bank; Jose Suarez; and Mary C. Rentschler.
    - Death papers: correspondence, 1948 March 5-May 27 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 7)
      Letters of praise to David Lawrence, journalist, in response to article/obituary he wrote about Gordon S. Rentschler. Including letters from James Forrestal, Secretary of Defense; Cardinal Spellman; Robert M. Sohngen, Justice; and George A. Brakeley.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence, 1948 March 8 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 8)
      Condolence letter to Frederick B. Rentschler from Ralph S. Danon, president of American Airlines, upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence, 1948 March 8, 11 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 9)
      Letter of condolence from Alfreada Link, including arrangements for Gordon S. Rentschler's funeral, Hamilton, Ohio.
    - National City Bank testimonial, 1948 March 9 (Offsite-box 6, Box Mem-45)
      In memoriam illuminated bound volume for Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - City Bank Farmers Trust Co. testimonial, 1948 March 10 (Offsite-box 6, Box Mem-46)
      In memoriam bound volume for Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Death papers: correspondence, document, 1948 March 11 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 10)
      Tribute/ eulogy to Gordon S. Rentschler by Grace Reah Johnson upon his death. Covering note to Mary C. Rentschler.
    - Consolidated Edison testimonial, 1948 March 12 (Offsite-box 6, Box Mem-48)
      In memoriam illustrated bound volume for Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company testimonial, 1948 March 17 (Offsite-box 6, Box Mem-49)
    - Princeton University testimonial, 1948 March 22 (Offsite-box 6, Box Mem-47)
    - Union Pacific Railroad testimonial, 1948 March 25, April 14 (Offsite-box 6, Box Mem-50)
      Memorial tribute (bound volume of minutes) from the Union Pacific Railroad in honor of Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Death papers: minutes, program, correspondence, 1948 March 25-June 17 (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 11)
      National Cash Register Company extract from minutes of meeting of board of directors in honor of Gordon S. Rentschler. Also condolence letters upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler from Ralph H. Tapscott and ?.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence A-B, 1948 March (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 12)
      Condolence letters (A-B) upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler from worldwide business colleagues to the chairman of the board, National City Bank, William G. Brady Jr., and vice president W. Randolph Burgess.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence C-D, 1948 March (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 13)
      Condolence letters (C-D) upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler from worldwide business colleagues to the chairman of the board, National City Bank, William G. Brady Jr., and vice president W. Randolph Burgess.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence E-H, 1948 March (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 14)
      Condolence letters (E-H) upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler from worldwide business colleagues to the chairman of the board, National City Bank, William G. Brady Jr., and vice president W. Randolph Burgess.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence K-R, 1948 March (Offsite-box Man-18, Folder 15)
      Condolence letters (K-R) upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler from worldwide business colleagues to the chairman of the board, National City Bank, William G. Brady Jr., and other NCB executives.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence S-W & miscellaneous, 1948 March (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 1)
      Condolence letters (S-W and miscellaneous) upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler from worldwide business colleagues to the chairman of the board, National City Bank, William G. Brady Jr., and other NCB executives.
    - Death papers: condolence telegrams, 1948 March (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 2)
      Condolence telegrams sent to National City Bank executives, New York City, upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence, 1948 April 4-October 29 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 3)
      Condolence correspondence from fellow alumni of Gordon S. Rentschler's at Princeton University. Dinner program in honor of GSR by Class of 1907 at Princeton University.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence, 1948 April 6-November 23 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 4)
      Condolence letter and reminiscence letter (April 5, 1929?) about Gordon S. Rentschler by Edward Antrim and Thomas A. Dorsey of Hamilton, Ohio, on behalf of Mary C. Rentschler.
    - Death papers: document, 1948 April 9 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 5)
      Resolution by the Miami Conservancy District of Dayton, Ohio, in honor of Gordon S. Rentschler for his work on flood control. Document signed by Edward A. Deeds.
    - Death papers: correspondence, 1948 April 15-19 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 6)
      Photocopies of legal correspondence re: will and petition of probate for Gordon S. Rentschler. Correspondents: John B. Hollister for Taft, Stettinius & Hollister or Cincinnati, Ohio, and Guy Cary of Shearman & Sterling & Wright, New York City (will & probate not included).
    - Death papers: correspondence, document, 1948 April 15-1950 December 28 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 7)
      Correspondence, programs, and documents re: tributes and the creation of a Princeton University memorial professorship in honor of Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Death papers: condolence correspondence, 1948 May 10 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 8)
      Condolence letter from Edward A. Deeds, president of the National Cash Register Company, Dayton, Ohio, to Mary C. Rentschler on behalf of the company, upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Home Insurance Co. testimonial, 1948 May 10 (Offsite-box 6, Box Mem-43)
    - Death papers: minutes, 1948 May 12 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 9)
      Minutes of the Ford Foundation paying tribute to Gordon S. Rentschler upon his death.
    - Death papers: correspondence, 1948 June 1 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 10)
      Letter from James M. Cox, publisher, to William S. Lambie, commiserating upon the death of Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Death papers: correspondence, 1948 June 4 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 11)
      Letter to Mary C. Rentschler and memorial tribute to Gordon S. Rentschler from the Young Men's Christian Association of Hamilton, Ohio.
    - Death papers: document, 1948 June 11 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 12)
      Memorial tribute to Gordon S. Rentschler by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
    - Death papers: correspondence, 1948 June 29 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 13)
      Leter from William G. Brady Jr., chairman of the board of National City Bank of New York, to Mary C. Rentschler, informing her of the appointment of Frederick B. Rentschler to the board of directors (in honor of Gordon S. Rentschler).
    - Death papers: correspondence (Adler-Hart), 1948 December 21-1950 July 19 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 14)
      Correspondence (Adler-Hart) to Henry B. Guthrie, secretary, Organization Committee of the Friends of Gordon S. Rentschler re: amounts offered (or declined) for the creation of a memorial fund, in alphabetical order by donor.
    - Death papers: correspondence (Henninger-Ziegler), 1948 December 21-1950 July 20 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 15)
      Correspondence (Henninger-Ziegler) to Henry B. Guthrie, secretary, Organization Committee of the Friends of Gordon S. Rentschler re: amounts offered (or declined) for the creation of a memorial fund, in alphabetical order by donor.
    - Death papers: correspondence, 1948 December-1950 December (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 16)
      Correspondence and a list of contributors (including amounts) to the Gordon S. Rentschler professorship memorial fund.
    - Death papers: correspondence, 1949 February 10 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 17)
      Photocopy of documents re: creation of plaque honoring Gordon S. Rentschler for the Princeton University faculty lounge. Letter from Donald Scott to Robert B. O'Connor.
    - Death papers: correspondence, 1950 April 27-1951 November 13 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 18)
      Correspondence to and from James H. Townsend, Eastham, Virginia, re: creation of the Gordon S. Rentschler professorship memorial fund.
    - Death papers: correspondence, 1955 Feb. 26; 1981 Mar. 30; 2000 Jan. 7 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 19)
      Photocopy of documents re: recipients of Gordon S. Rentschler professorship, Princeton University. Professors are
      1) Lester V. Chandler
      2) Burton G. Malkiel
      3) Alan S. Binder
    - Death papers: publication, 1967 June 9 (Offsite-box Man-19, Folder 20)
      Booklet commemorating Princeton University 60th reunion class of 1907.
    - Genealogy / History: BUCKLEY, George, 1935 December-1936 January (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 1)
      Obituaries for George Buckley, National City Bank executive. Bound volume of photocopied news clippings; NCB "Number Eight" publication dedicated to him.
    - Genealogy / History: CASSADY, Ann Rentschler, 1994 (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 2)
      Funeral service program, Boca Raton, Florida.
    - Genealogy / History: DEEDS, Edward A., 1986-1996 (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 3)
      Miscellaneous correspondence, news clippings, and publications re: the Deeds home, Moraine Farm, in Keetering, Ohio.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER (General), circa 1830s-1980s (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 4)
      Historical research by various family members.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER (Holzaepfel), circa 1896-1965 (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 5)
      Photocopies of family tree originally commissioned by George A. Rentschler Sr. (1896), and subsequently translated. Also a listing of Rentschler names throughout the United States.
    - Original architectural plans for Locust Valley, Long Island home (Paul D. Cravath name on plan), 1929 (Offsite-box Ovz-3)
      RENTSCHLER family. Architectural plans for home on Duck Pond Road, Long Island, New York.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER (General), 1939 August 14 (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 6)
      Photocopy of news clipping re: Rentschler home at 933 Fifth Avenue, New York City, that was demolished.
    - Surveys, subdivisions, maps, and architectural drawings, circa 1923-1961 (Offsite-box Ovz-5 (cylinder))
      RENTSCHLER - maps of properties belonging to Gordon S. Rentschler and Mary C. Rentschler in Hamilton, Butler County, Ohio, including subdivisions of land among family members.
    - Map of Butler County, OH, 1961, 1967 (Offsite-box Ovz-3)
      Rentschler family. Two maps:
      1) Rentschler property in Butler County, Ohio
      2) Butler County, Ohio
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, Frederick B., 1920-1996 (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 7)
      Miscellaneous materials re: FBR's work in aeronautical industry and Renbrook home, Connecticut:
      1) News clipping re: FBR involvement in early aero industry (1920)
      2) Obituary
      3) Pamphlet commemorating FBR's work (1985)
      4) News clipping re: Renbrook home
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, Frederick B., 1945 September 1-1951 March 31 (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 8)
      Photocopies of correspondence found with publication (Box Man-19, Folder 15):
      1) James Forrestal, Secretary of the Navy, thanking FBR for WWII work
      2) Letters congratulating FBR on Pratt & Whitney book
      3) Legion d'Honneur awarded to FBR by Henry Bonnet, Ambassador
    - Frederick B. Rentschler The Pratt Law & Whitney Story, 1950 (Offsite-box 7, Box Mem-52)
    - Frederick B. Rentschler bound obituaries, 1956 (Offsite-box 7, Box Mem-53)
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, George, 1949 March 31 (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 9)
      Photocopy of an obituary.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, George A., Jr., circa 1920s? (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 10)
      News clipping re: appointment of George Adam Rentschler Jr. as Director of Miami Conservancy District, Ohio.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, George A., Sr., 1923 (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 11)
      Bound volume of obituaries. Photograph.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, George A., Sr., 1923 (Offsite-box Man-20, Folder 12)
      Bound volume of obituaries.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, George A., Sr., 1923 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 1)
      Photocopies of bound volume of obituaries.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, George A., Sr. / SCHWAB, Phoebe, 1916-1923 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 2)
      Bound volume of obituaries with photographs.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, George A., Sr. / SCHWAB, Phoebe, 1916-1923 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 3)
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, George A., Sr. / SCHWAB, Phoebe, 1916-1923 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 4)
      Photocopies of obituaries and testimonies.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, Gordon S., 1948 March (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 5)
      News clippings of obituaries.
    - Gordon S. Rentschler bound obituaries, 1948 March (Offsite-box 5, Box Mem-42)
      Bound volume of newspaper obituaries re: death of Gordon S. Rentschler.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, Gordon S., 1948 March-May (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 6)
      National City Bank in-house publication, "Number Eight," in memory of GSR. Also, National Cash Register Company obituary.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, Henry A., 1941 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 7)
      In memoriam booklet honoring HAR. Photograph inside.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, Peter E., 1970 July 8 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 8)
      Correspondence re: 50 years of PER at Hamilton Foundry. Biographical notes on his life.
    - Genealogy / History: RENTSCHLER, Robert P., 1915 June 30 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 9)
      Photocopy of obituary.
    - Genealogy / History: SCHWAB, Mary, 1964 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 10)
      News clippings re: 90th birthday of Mary Schwab (Mrs. Peter E. Schwab).
    - Genealogy / History: SCHWAB, Peter, 1913 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 11)
      Obituaries for Peter Schwab.
    - Newspaper obituary re: Peter Schwab, 1913 September 15 (Offsite-box Ovz-3)
    - Genealogy / History: SOHN, Henry, 1915 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 12)
      Photocopy of obituary. See Box Osz-3, Folder # for originals.
    - Newspaper obituary re: Henry Sohn, 1915 January 18 (Offsite-box Ovz-3)
    - Genealogy / History: Butler County and Hamilton, Ohio histories, circa 1913-1996 (Offsite-box Man-21, Folder 13)
      General historical information re: Butler County and Hamilton, Ohio, including the Great Flood of 1913; a historical sketch by Dan Millikin; obituary of Edward Antrim; publication--"Ohio, the Buckeye State" (1935).
  - Subseries I.D. Helen Rentschler Waldon (1890–1967) [HRW]
    Helen Rentschler Waldon was born in 1890, the only daughter of Phoebe Schwab Rentschler and George Adam Rentschler Sr. The bulk of the correspondence in this group was written to her by her family and reflects her primary role as a dutiful daughter and loyal sibling and wife. On September 29, 1906, Phoebe wrote to Helen at the Ogontz School in Pennsylvania: "Well my dear daughter be a good child as you always have been let no one lead you astray, but be the same true simple little girl you always have been" (Box Man-22, Folder 2). Helen's formal education, away from home, indicates an egalitarian attitude toward a female child, albeit couched in traditional patronizing language. Three years later her mother counsels thriftiness in economic hard times, and we indirectly learn that her father, George Adam Rentschler Sr., enjoyed privileged information as a bank official:
    "You know Papa is always much concerned about his people especially the little shop & he takes it upon himself to help them keep the wolf from their doors. No doubt there will be much suffering among the working classes. In fact money is so scarce that it is wise for all classes to be watchful & saving. Things are more serious than the newspapers tell, but it is wise for the papers to make light of it, for it would scare those who have their savings in the banks & cause much trouble. The banks of Hamilton are solid & people have no need to fear, but then it is hard to make them understand & believe when they have their all placed in safe keeping. Papa is in a position to know the circumstances, as he is a director in two Hamilton banks & on the inside workings of the other three.... So my dear child do your share of economical financing too" (circa 1908/9; Box Man-22, Folder 2).